welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
if i press record bonita anytime you're
ready
okay welcome to the psycho technology
playground hosted by the stoa
this though is a place to cohere
in dialogue around what matters most
here at the knife's edge of the moment
yeah so just an announcement um so i
think i'm going to uh take a break
uh after this this uh session i
gonna try to um abandon all my
commitments
for a month um so uh
the question is what should we do i have
completely
um come with um
no preparation usually usually the night
before
i get these hits of what i want to do i
do have your questions from a couple of
times ago we could we could
revisit that or we could just let
the topic or the theme uh
self-organize uh through your
participation
that would be kind of interesting
or we could sit in silence is silence is
a type of coherence
maybe it's even a type of dialogue i'm
not sure
i like silence
so where my eyes are going are
on the um
those pages behind lisa norton
and i'm wondering why they like they run
along like a
series or storyboard or something you
don't have to share but i noticed
my curiosity oh my apartment is
full of maps everywhere
my mapping mania
but uh yeah i i realized that
it's a long story that i won't bore
everyone with
but working toward
the table of contents of my book turned
into some kind of a digital game
ah cool yeah it looked like a storyboard
of some sort
you know what it reminds me of um
there's i think it's in a hundred years
of solitude
where the whole town is losing their
memory
so they they they write they write the
names and uses of things on everything
but then
they they lose their memory of how to
read them you know the whole thing just
kind of like
well yeah that's funny i just read that
yesterday
yeah so how does is that how the story
goes um
yeah it was like they they become
insomniacs
somehow and then they all lose their
memory and then
the main father's like yeah let's put
labels on everything
but then he has this like cathartic
moment where he's like well we can't
just do labels we also need to say what
they are
and then when he wakes up he looks at
how ridiculous it is that everything
has a label when he like cures the
insomnia
that's a great book i read a long time
ago um
it's be nice to revisit it
and i just watched memento last night
ah and what's that what's that one about
um it's a
mystery or a thriller in reverse
so it starts at the end and it moves
forward
i mean that's what's innovative about it
as a film but the
the plot is this man loses his
short-term memory and so he's constantly
writing notes
to try to maintain some thread as he's
trying to solve this mystery
and it it's it's a brilliant film
but it says a lot about the role of
memory
and the way we reconstruct memory and
the the potential for being used when we
don't have
contact with reality over time
yeah there's something about you know
there's a lot of discussion about how
uh the internet never forgets right
everything's captured and
stays and archived forever
there's a short film where people in the
future have this ability to
to switch their eyes so they record
everything like they're kind of like
cyborgs and and it
ends up driving them crazy because it's
about two people in a relationship
and um
something odd happens like this she's
flirting with someone else and
and he just keeps watching it over and
over and over again to try to interpret
it and
and then they're trying to have a
conversation and the ways in which we
slide the truth to update it uh yeah
black mirror episode
uh the ways in which we slide the truth
to update the new reality
you know so someone will say something
they're like oh no no no and then
they'll flash
the actual recording on the on the to
say no that's not the way it happened
and uh yeah
and um it's it's again it's playing with
this notion of
um
what matters most to people you know we
think that remembering
getting the facts right being able to
point to the facts
um that this makes this helps us make
sense
but it actually uh makes us crazy
um yeah it was just before this uh
session thinking about how
society civilization we look back on
like uh pre-text um civilizations
whereas just oral tradition
um and then like switched up the thought
of like from a future
civilization looking back um on
and like thinking about civilizations
that didn't have
these like yeah digital recording means
um in that same way and that kind of
yeah you get this precision but you also
but there's yeah there's something
that's kind of lost in there or
like there's a bit of a trade-off
perhaps
yeah you know in interestingly i was
just finishing up this
chapter on writing and it ends just
right toward the end it ends
it quotes hannah arendt and she writes
um
the light that illuminates processes of
action
appears only at their end frequently
when all the participants
are dead and then
this notion of
this notion is of when you live through
complex
times you're the you're the least able
to the people that are living through
the complexity
are the least able to make sense of it
it's always retrospectively made sense
either by
themselves in the future or by or by
historians
and i you know i put it in the article
because it's you know it's for the
it's a submission for a book on you know
this time between worlds that's
where uh the
that's kind of like the calling the
anchoring theme
and i know in the book there's going to
be
a lot of really intelligent people
um claiming that such and such a
framework is
can make sense of the world we live in
and i'm basically saying
uh no it's just it's the way we
the way it is we're the least able to
make sense of it
um and that will only happen
you know when most of us are dead um
i i use the metaphor the only the best
we can do is
we could we can we can create
seeds that um don't that won't
um that won't grow in our time and
they're not for us
um yeah so it's this way of working
in unpredictability and uncertainty
and knowing that shouldn't be surprised
that
its own richness is is hidden from us
and then you know of course then the
question is then how do we
how do we choose to act
now let's see rainey's got an
interesting thought here
yeah so it is um zach's it comes from
uh zach will be doing a contribution
and um it's the organizing kind of theme
the time between worlds
yes focusing on facts is a sign of
attachment distress that's very
interesting because
i was just watching a video the other
day
um where that was happening and that's
exactly the problem
that you since you get from there um
yeah and you know what's interesting
are people who are postmodern and they
understand that others people's world's
view is not factual
but they're but then the way they relate
to theirs is very
like you know saying things like well
it's obvious
right you know um we can agree that
there are no aliens
on this earth but it's obvious blah blah
blah blah you know things like that so
this notion of facts um
yeah is very interesting
oh yeah so here's a quote just like we
need a memory we need a forgot
forgot to read um
yeah hannah talks about that she talks
about how
um how much forgiveness
is important in the human condition
because
the actions we take um have potential
you know repercussions especially
in today's age um where we can't we
don't we can't
really foretell that all the
consequences
but we have to be responsible for our
actions so it's up to
the human you know it's up to the
community to have
the power of forgiveness um
do you have any thoughts on this cancel
culture
craze that's happening right now and the
conversations surrounding it
um
i think i think these things
are tempests in a teapot
you know like can't cancel culture is a
big thing now
nobody actually um
you have to ask what do you get what are
you getting canceled from
you know what are you getting canceled
from oh i get canceled from twitter
okay you know let's just shoot me now
um i think it's more
you know we're such dramaturgists you
know it's more of this
it's it's made up drama
um of course people means a lot to
people
um but i think that um
it just shows you know that that there's
there's shared power you know there's
there's power in connecting on the
internet
and then there's power with you know
people who
who can cancel you out
it doesn't it i don't really
i don't really understand why it's such
a big deal
i mean if i say something here and i get
cancelled from the store yeah i
would hurt my feelings but you know
the internet is not
the neither the meaning
nor the basis nor the prerequisite to to
life
um
and i think it's impossible for you to
get canceled from the stoa benita just
just for the
record oh i'll try
yeah so um i
you know to me it's like all this
reality
is like real you know watching reality
tv except you know it's kind of has a
nice script
i don't you know there's so many um oh
jj
yeah um so for example
there's so many cool things happening on
the internet like brett weinstein just
had a round table with a bunch of
black intellectuals and glenn laurie and
john mcwhorten
and camilla can't remember his last name
and
um those conversations are are
really intense um it
it was very interesting dynamics uh uh
bret actually looked a little bit naive
at some point you know
um which was very interesting so
to me it's like um
cancel control it's not that interesting
to me but
why where there are um
high quality uh
very interesting conversations going on
why they don't appear in these spaces
i mean he's got a decent number of
subscribers
but they never appear in the spaces
where all this other
drama is going on um
so um
that's that's an interesting question
that's more interesting question to me
uh why does that level of discourse
um not go viral not penetrate
um
for the people that he had on his show
you know they are vulnerable to
being canceled by their own colleagues
you know that they're
they don't fit a stereotype um
they they uh um
yeah so part i guess that's what's part
of candle culture is
is is the the
the uh self manipulation of mass
consciousness or something
you know it's like the processes of of
only this
uh should appear in the public space
and these implicit mechanisms these
implicit social obligations
to amplify
that
what's what's interesting to me lately
um
and of course these these topics all
have a shelf life of like you know three
months no one talks about covet anymore
uh the riots are gone now it's cancelled
culture i mean it's just
the attention span on this but what's
really interesting to me
is the predominance of
white intellectual liberals in the black
lives matter
movements and their effect of
effectively co-opted
the energy for uh who knows what
you know there's there's a a lot of
interesting
uh there was an interesting video of a
black
police officer who was telling the story
from his
his point of view um so when he's on the
line with a
black lives matter protest
he says he's most often looking at
people
uh in you know there's many more white
people there
of a certain demographic and he says and
oftentimes when like
a black person and he told a couple
story will come and say you know and try
to have a real conversation like what is
it
like from your perspective they get
yelled at like why are you talking to
him because
the the the identity that they're
casting on him is not as a also a black
person
but as a policeman you know so like how
these
how these identities and the us and them
and the we
um they're all kind of they're all kind
of
in motion right now um
yeah so um
what really bothers me where i
um feel
some key importance is is that
naive white
liberals think they can speak for the
black
experience in america i think it's it's
a
huge mistake i think it's a huge mistake
and i think um i don't even think
um it comes from a place of compassion
and actual interest i think i think
there's something else going on there
i think it's some kind of just overall
resentment
and the impression that if you're a
white
liberal and you're resentful of your
situation you don't have your own
platform or something like that
something very strange is going on with
that
but i'm not quite sure what it is
um can i ask a question or should i chat
no uh questions are better i can't
follow the chat
um well i wanted to i was i've been
interested in um you know
kind of what you were talking about it's
like um with that but it's also there's
sort of this you know interest in
political revolution
and people into that and i guess i've
had the belief for a while that
um i guess i don't have a lot of faith
in it without
um i guess the spirituality that you
were talking about last week which i saw
your video a couple days ago and
i loved it and i'm curious if you have
any ideas of sort of how to bridge those
together um i guess in my head i really
feel like they need to become
allies in some way because obviously
people's intentions
are good but sometimes the executions
aren't and i feel like sometimes
have spirituality can help you
be in touch with some of the things that
people are sort of trying to have at a
surface level
um i don't know yeah so i would say
and i'll map i'm gonna share an
experience i had when i was younger
and um so it could be a complete
projection
but when i think back on the time and i
think i told this story a little bit in
another session when i lived in
california we lived in
berkeley uh we were a bunch of like
i mean not me so much i was quite naive
but i lived with people that
were students at the art institute
we always were black were all very it
was very very
trendy we went to these performance
things
um sex
pistols radical feminists crazy radical
feminists
and we hosted the z we used to host the
zimbabwean
liberation army at our house when they
were down at oakland
communist center doing their thing you
know when
zimbabwe was rhodesia
and um now of course this is all
retrospective
sense making when i when i lean into the
energy i had then for that
um i i have to admit that like the
energy was in the concept of liberating
zimbabwe
didn't have any insight and in fact it
was
very strange when they were there
because
they just kind of took over the place
and it's so obvious that
we weren't part of their world you know
they had guns and walkie-talkies
they were very militant we were like we
were like kind of like
young lost kids you know
not in the hippie generation not in the
rap generation
we were like into lou reed and john cage
and
brian eno and
uh patty smith and so it's really
when i think about it it's like a whole
cultural thing it's had
the energy of resentment and alienation
but then these things like zimbabwean
thing comes along and you
in in it you kind of package it you
weave that into
something that uh is
not really what's your experience you
know it comes along for the ride
you go along for the ride and i think
this is true for
uh young people um it's it's part of
the energy of new generations it's part
of their function
right to um scare the out
old people who want to hold on um
so there's something about that energy
and
um that i think has to be
not only allowed but understood
in in in it'll change context you know
so you can't say well back in the day
we were this and now kids this it's just
it's just this kind of generational
energy
that doesn't mean to say you know you
don't hold your part which is a critique
or a shaping or a leadership part
um or to support um
that that uh shaping into
a new stable reality or something that
uh
you can be proud of as human beings but
um
so for me
um what did what was the
what was the topic of your question i
gotta roll it into
i guess i mean i guess i've been in a
little bit more of a
not that way spirituality spirituality
political revolution if there's any way
that they could be friends
or i always think of maybe the idea that
they're allies um yeah
so so so having said that
it means that there's something about
uh generations that they have this
revolutionary energy
but they don't have they need it should
be they come
into it grounded into something like the
new world needs to be formed in their
spiritual consciousness by the time they
get this energy
and what happens is we enter this energy
without any freaking clue of who we are
and this is like foundationally we don't
build whole human beings we think
we basically um put that off
until way later in life and and i think
that's
that that's where i was going with this
question so like the energy's there
but there's no um
each generation they don't
there's no there's no grounding uh
power or you know sovereignty in that
generation
there's there's we infantilize in many
cases
um are the the students so um not that
that doesn't
won't be captured but but um
[Music]
p each generation needs to understand
um themselves
in a more grounded way much earlier than
when they take to the streets
and then they have then there's
something powerful to say
um i had a online
um me class with
students graduating from uconn and i
you know i said to them um do you ever
talk about that like in
15 years every or 20 years you know by
the time you're my age
every everyone who runs everything is
going to be dead
and that you are the people you know you
are the people to occupy those positions
it's not and then it was a real mind
blower to them and they talked about how
um their experience we felt into that
and their experience was like
they were standing on a void because
their whole lives there's
you know there's people behind them
younger people coming and older people
to follow like it's a seamless train
and they didn't get that like and when
they felt into that they're like well
well well you know like
um it was just this this scary void
um and i think that um
we can do a better job with
human souls let's say
[Music]
in our education system
part of it is you know we used to each
children used to have it
be able to rely on a sense of place
right
very strong sense of place since
more sense of ethnography your ethnic
family these were all kinds of
structures that would anchor
people in who are they where do they
come from
and from there where were we going now
it's just to like
where are we going you know it's just
like oh where are we going you know
they know the train is moving fast but
there's no
there's there's no place to uh
to create from
and that's kind of you know i know that
that was
that was partially true for me um
i think it's it might be even more true
now
um
and somebody asked one of the questions
is all this how are
children being affected by all these
addicting and virtual spaces and
i think it makes that more true like
everything is
dis displaced um
but that energy is still there i mean
and that's that's
that's good energy for the human system
to have
and work with
it may be part of um that this
completely i'm just
ex temporary and just showing you how my
my mind works so um
you know maybe partially the reason it's
it's it's
could could be related to um the very
strong need for
uh young people to split identities you
know
like i'm not so to be very very clear
if i'm lgb q
or you know all these like uh the
categories of identity have become very
very thin
and maybe that's part of a reaction
of you know needing to
find some ground but the problem with
those is
they're not experiential as much as
again yet again
uh some people relate to them because
they've had that actual experience but a
lot of people relate to them as
concepts and categories it's a
conceptual adoption of
something um
uh rather than having lived that
experience
um which is not to take that experience
away from the people who have lived and
examined
um and been thoughtful about their
experience but
that's not for you to project on
you know um
yeah and that's where spirituality comes
in the sense of
insolent the sense of who am i what is
my purpose
what's meaningful for me what's real for
me
and um
it's always going to be a minority
position the closer you get to your
your own experience the more unique it
is so
um
how do we how do we make the
that that arise in public space so
i you know it ties into i was talking
the other day i was very interested in
anecdotal
uh anecdotal evidence or
um having people to speak about their
own experiences
anecdotally as part of the information
ecology and
um yeah and
all your all your comments here
are great because it starts to put
together some of the things
um that we were talking about um
but there's some interesting i i saw uh
um it's why that book sand talk is so i
think we talked about this last
last time why that book sand talk is so
powerful for people
because it's it's completely and he
talks in completely anecdotal ways about
his experience and his family and his
tribes and
uh people like kind of starving for that
that reality
i have a question if you can hear me in
the bus yes
i'm curious about in intentionality
you spoke about it before yeah
like how do you go to put it to a story
or a feeling or
principle or like what is the connection
between
intention and and these things associate
yeah that's a very tricky question so um
the the reason one of the reasons why
the question of intel
tensionality is a pickle for us
is because we set it up with a mental
model
that can't answer the question and that
would be like your story so for example
in general when we ask the question how
does
intention
relate to me taking action or choice or
something like that right
we have a mental model of a billiard
ball
there's the intention then how does it
move to choice
how does choice move to action so we
can't answer the
question because the the the mental
model we ask the question into
makes impossible to answer because
uh because of that we have to we have to
really wrap our
minds away from this intention causes
this that causes that it causes it
causes that
um so um
there's a phrase that alicia
guarrero uses to get around this she
says
uh intention flows into action
and you can't find where one begins and
the other ends
so this is different right so um so
so the language cuts
makes makes too too coarse a cut there
was intention
then there was action and she's like it
doesn't work like that
this is it's like my buddhist cult my
doll is calling
where's your feet on the ground where's
your head and you get confused because
you've
cut you have this linear model of
segmented
your body's a segmented thing so it
doesn't make sense for you to say my
head is on the ground
because the mental model of where is
your feet
precludes you from saying that because
as soon as you do that
you segment this linear spatial person
right so it's the same thing with the
question of intention if you
catch yourself asking a question and
you're like
when does intention cause
behavior or when does intention cause
choice that if then structure
has created a gap that's not there and
therefore it's impossible
to answer the question so then you have
to
really with your mind
and um
try to get underneath what are you
trying to ask
what do you what what is there for you
to solve
and um that can be
interesting practice um
but you'll never be able to answer the
question if you
if you have a if you if you're holding
onto a mental model that makes the
question impossible to answer
so there you go
yeah you've talked a few a couple times
before about how
the if then propositions uh kind of
they they like breaking down and
especially like in science and making
science not um i can't remember exactly
how you put it
but do you have any sources or somewhere
i can kind of look deeper into that
um yeah so
um
so anything on complexity
um um
i hate to recommend some of the books
they're just so
hard to read my chapter in this meta
modern is gonna
is about time cause time change and
causality
it's really asking ourselves what's our
mental
model of time is that useful
what's our mental model of change is
that useful what
what's our mental model causality which
i go into this thing that i just spoke
with rasmus about
um and then um
there's there's
um so um
yeah so alexia what your
j-u-a-r-r-e-r-o
uh dynamics dynamical systems theory
um that's a
that's not a fun book to read um
yeah so mutual causality and buddhism
general systems theory uh
we have to get i do bring that up in the
in the chapter
um that you know that
our mental our mental structures are
causally implicated in the real world
um the buddhists though then never asked
well how does that happen
if we have you know the westerners then
we wanted to
create a built billiard ball chain
chain causal link between mental
structures and intention and action
um whereas the buddhist path you just
get the insight and the question kind of
fall drops away until you know you have
to
speak about it and then then you're
stuck again but
um yeah
i don't know any good sources that put
it together the way
uh you know there's a lot of sources i
draw from but i don't
know if anyone speaks to it directly you
can
if you look at my articles i have some
articles on medium
in the publications called perspectives
on complexity or perspectives from
complexity and they play around with
some of this and it's pretty easy to
read
[Music]
i use a lot of white head concepts from
whitehead
so um one of the
one of the that i see general system
series here
so i'm going i'm pushing it beyond
general systems theory because
one other thing about general systems
theory
is it replaces if then you know with
with systems change and phase dates and
uh
phase dynamics and threshold events
which is okay
but if you notice they are forced to use
the language of complex adaptive systems
so everything's always adapting to
everything else and
dynamical systems theory and the problem
with that
is it um by definition
um yeah strategy without design is great
um by definition if you're caught in the
notion of
you're adapting or responding to
something
and everything is adapting and
responding to you then eventually
the whole system closes in on itself and
becomes a perpetual motion machine this
is
this is actually the frame of mind we
have
today around climate we're adapting to
climate climate's adapting to us
the whole thing is global everything is
just reaction
there's no there's no possibility in
this mental model
to do something de novo to make a move
that's not in it in all our science and
all our discourse in all our responses
to these
things create these closed loops of
perpetual reaction cycles this is
basically the mind
that approaches our our climate change
problems
and our um medical problems
you know we create a vaccine the the
virus reacts to the vaccine then we
react to
the mutation of the virus and this thing
so
the question is we move from if then
thinking to
complex adaptive systems which brings in
the environment that's
good uh but complex adaptive systems
i think is highly problematic um
for these reasons so um
can we move
you know even our markets are like that
so can we move to
um something that works with
um what i call complex potential states
so what is potential right now not
what are you responding to something
that's emergent from within the
potential that's in you
right what is potential right now
almost absent the landscape in which
you're acting
what is potential right now what is
potential in you
um so not something you're responding to
or reacting to as a thought
or um
is this kind of i say
something very quite controversial
in my paper and that is i say
that in the anthropocene we have to
learn to be the first mover
so can we make a a move can we
act completely outside of the
that that way that paradigm of action
and reaction
gaming everybody gaming everybody else
you know
that's this is this is cancel cultures
like that
all these things are so recursive
so that's an interesting question um
um and it requires i think a
spiritual approach um to
to um
it's not a question to answer it's kind
of uh
it's not completely deconstructive
either but it's kind of uh
yeah it could be we could say reboots
your intentional
space you know reboots
um but this the very highly
uh imaginative article you know i
try to just do some of that work getting
around
around some of these you know
persistent errors of the modern mind
um
bonita uh earlier on in the conversation
you were talking about forgiveness as
being a
necessary stance
um i'm just wondering it when you're
talking about
forgiveness there if what you would
say your source code would be for that
that's a very that's you know that's
like
that's like honey to be that kind of
question for me
[Music]
it makes me want to come back next week
[Laughter]
um forgiveness well when you i
you know i quoted hannah arendt um
actually i feel always feel my
self-contract
uh around the notion of forgiveness and
and um so
let me let me look at that it's pretty
clear for me i'm not
i'm not saying everyone uh
[Music]
everyone feels there's different there's
different
meanings around uh forgiveness but
one of the things that i don't like
about the word
is um
uh see true forgiveness cuts the karmic
loop
cuts the karmic co cord right
we don't have that kind of forgiveness
today we have forgiveness that then
the other person put something in their
ledger like you know
okay now i have a little iou or
something that i can
cash in um but true
uh forgiveness completely cuts the
karmic chord
so it's actually more like forgetting
like just forgetting
like completely forgetting and starting
over
so uh now i think that's what hana
meant if you read the
excerpt in context and i think she does
talk about forgetting and
in her peculiar way then shows that even
that's a problematic word but
it's this notion of really um
and so this is something that confuses
people about me because
i have been i had this woman here
uh one of my workshops and she stayed
here
and um she didn't have any money so i
like to do the workshop for free and i
picked up the station and drove her back
and forth she was a student of
gentleman's kind of interesting that way
um i don't know
and then on the second night she was
talking
to my partner of 30 years my
quote-unquote
non-married husband and
she was like bonding with him like she
was drinking beer and that's okay
she was like just having fun but
she started making fun of the way i
drive and then
and i drive like crazy when i have
students in the car because they're
always asking me questions like this and
i'm trying to drive you know i get
really like
uh i just get very lucy about how i
drive
and and it turned into one of those like
yeah you know brought out the
stereotypes of why i can't drive and
this and that now
i didn't mind that sandy was doing that
because
he was just kind of like playing along
it was just light but it really bothered
me that she was like that
like really bothered me i thought it was
completely
uh unethical
i thought it was like a sin right and so
i told her the next morning i and when
she saw me coming around the corner she
just like
really blushed because she knew like how
really unfair she was being to have that
kind of conversation in the context it
was a very intense workshop so people
feel really raw it was just mean it was
basically
very mean so the next morning
when driving you know um the next
morning
i just told her i said she said oh you
know i didn't mean to do blah blah blah
i know it was bad
and i said this is how i experienced it
you know and i just said i fed you i
gave you your
your the you know a set of clothes blah
blah blah
and then this is what you did right i
just said
that was my experience and then i said
um and she was getting very hysterical
and i said
um you know it's not that big a problem
because these things don't they don't
hang out i don't get hangovers from them
i'm not gonna like every time i look at
you have a bad
taste in my mouth they just i just said
don't you know
and this but this bothered her even more
like the fact that it
like i mean basically it was what it was
i thought it was mean right and i told
her so
boom done and she just couldn't deal
that was worse for her like she just
didn't know what to do with herself
right she thought i was being really
mean to her back but i
i wasn't like i was just like all right
whatever i did something mean
it hurt me and i got on with it so
um so people think i'm mean because of
that
uh and then it gets very complex in
human society
because people think forgiveness should
come with this social obligation that's
infinite or something and that's more of
this
recursive reaction action cycle
but forgiveness is did i forgive her
well i didn't make it not mean she was
mean
i don't want to take away the act do you
see what i'm saying like forgiveness is
like well
i don't know uh
but
there was nothing you know it it it's
impermanent it comes and it went
and she's not an evil person it's just
it was just something mean she did and
it hurt me
and today is dif you know today is not
that um
i get the impression she was scarred for
life
but i'm not sure um
yeah so that's that's my
it's not a source called unforgiveness
but i think you know
that's how i relate when i what you know
source code has to do with what's your
embodied experience around this word
you know um
for me a lot of these teachings that
i've come to
practice or be come from watching nature
you know a dog gets run over
accidentally you know
there's a couple of things watching
animals and watching nature but also
understanding this
there's something we do when a tree
blows down
and ruins my car or
breaks my leg uh that's bad
but i don't project all this
it doesn't it doesn't erode me
psychologically the same as if some
crazy violent person came with a pipe
and broke my leg
and at some point it's better to just
understand people and these events as
nature also
and not project so much of your
self-importance on
why were they mean to me you know
why was the tree mean to me no
um that's not my work my work to do at
the end of the day
so bonita yeah
i um yeah wow i appreciate your
like how much you just uh late i feel
like you sort of lay
yourself open in these stories sometimes
so just like
just go um
and i i you know you're speaking about
speaking from experience and then
doing it um
and i'm thinking right now just what you
were saying about mental models earlier
as well
and just that it depends which what i'm
understanding is it depends which mental
model
you're using that word from um
and ria back often talks about sort of
dropping it
like just dropping the thing like it
feels like it
and and um i'm part of a learning
experiment um called the liminal space
agency
that uh we use sort of a
this idea of like you have to step out
of
the one paradigm into another entirely
um yeah when you were talking about
recording earlier
um and you know these people are
recording with their eyes
and then it just going down the tubes i
had this sense of like well that's
existing within a particular
um mental model context
that is not based in that version of
forgiveness that
uh you're talking about or you know
reaching for
um and
because i'm having this experience now
where we're using recordings
and listening to our conversations or
each other's conversations
and then having conversations about
those and it's recursive
and it's within this um
experiment in a mental model that
is post-judgment
that is um
yeah we're working to not
take it personally and to shift into
being able to see what happens kind of
in that way it's like oh this is
this is what's happening this is what
we're working with
um and what do we deeply want
and that's why i feel like what you're
talking about last week with the
around will feels really powerful
because it's about looking at what moves
us
um and what's happening
the two together which creates like a
creative tension between the two
i'm observing what's happening and i'm
observing what's moving me what what i
seem to
be drawn to and playing with that
creative tension
improvising within that yeah
i mean
these are all good practices to to
to take a look at what's under the hood
right you know
your perspectives um
they're not the point of living but they
can they can free up
a lot of processing uh capacity in your
nervous system
if you're not running mental models and
recordings and memories and
reinterpretations of memories and
and you know just only
there's only so much work the thing can
do
and there's a lot more life to be lived
than that
um
i'd rather cook
cook in a restaurant all my life than
spend that
my work doing you know all that effort
doing that you know like
i think there's i think they're
fascinating experience i think they have
a purpose
but uh
[Music]
uh interested in versions of spiritual
yeah so um
[Music]
one of the questions that i need to
figure out is
and again i say this i think every time
we're on the stove and that is like what
is
what is is this could this group be
stably
um meet to uh talk about things
a little more deeper um have what i call
monstrous conversations
um um
do you know do i have the time am i
willing to do that
uh the kinds of stuff that get excavated
for example
in my master's course where we're
together for two years is really
uh phenomenal and
um yeah and i haven't you know
uh i think you know i hold
back
in these sessions so uh yeah
i think that's uh there's it's a really
interesting question
um yeah um but
it has to be just
take the time it takes to be answered
and just like that it's 11 o'clock
that goes by fast um
no peter
thank you so much for this uh
space here um i am going to
be taking a break
and probably come back in a different
format
but not sure what that format will be
and um this is for writing
the stella runs on the gift economy
your presence here has always been a
gift to me and to each other
please continue to give
and to receive and
do that in equal portions
okay
thank you so much thank you benita
thank you have a great break